<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Reflections upon the late horrid conspiracy contrived by some of the French court to murther His Majesty in Flanders and for which Monsieur Grandvall, one of the assassinates, was executed.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 79KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 21 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A58383</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13337336</idno>
  <idno type="VID">99113</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2248524181</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing R729</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R14393</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">13337336</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A58383)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 99113)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 474:4)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Reflections upon the late horrid conspiracy contrived by some of the French court to murther His Majesty in Flanders and for which Monsieur Grandvall, one of the assassinates, was executed.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 35 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Richard Baldwin ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1692.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="personal_name">Grandvall, --  Monsieur.</term>
               <term type="personal_name">William --  III, --  King of England, 1650-1702.</term>
               <term type="geographic_name">Great Britain --  History --  William and Mary, 1689-1702 --  Sources.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-07 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-10 </date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-10 </date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="half_title">
            <pb facs="tcp:99113:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:99113:1"/>
            <p>REFLECTIONS UPON THE Late Horrid Conspiracy Contrived by some of the <hi>FRENCH</hi> COURT, To Murther His MAJESTY in <hi>Flanders.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:99113:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:99113:2"/>
            <p>REFLECTIONS Upon the LATE <hi>Horrid Conspiracy</hi> Contrived by Some of the <hi>FRENCH COƲRT,</hi> TO Murther His MAJESTY IN FLANDERS: And for which Monsieur GRAND<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>VALL, one of the Assassinates, was Executed.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed for <hi>Richard Baldwin,</hi> near the <hi>Oxford-Arms</hi> in <hi>Warwick-Lane.</hi> 1692.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:99113:3"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:99113:3"/>
            <head>REFLECTIONS ON THE Grand Conspiracy, &amp;c.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>ERE is a Plot with a Witness! fully Enquired into, and Proved, and the Traytor punished: Nor has Providence left the least colour for Enemies to cavil about the Truth of a Conspiracy, <hi>To Take away His Majesty's Life,</hi> when the Conspirator himself has obliged us with an ample Confession of his Crime. It's but seldom, that Designs against the Lives of Princes come to be believed, till the Execution of them puts them beyond doubt; and for the most part, the world is inclinable enough to suspect, That something lies hid under every Discovery that is said to be made of Treason, until the Blow actually given, puts too late a stop to their Incredulity.</p>
            <p>But this <hi>French Ass<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ssinate,</hi> tho he has with a Courage worthy of a better Cause, paid down his own, for a De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sign to take away one of the most Illustrious Lives upon earth; yet, it seems, he durst not trust the Eternal state of his Soul, to a <hi>Jesuitical Equivocation</hi> at his Death; but chose rather by a free, open Confession, to disoblige
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:99113:4"/> his Masters that set him on to perpetrate the Villany, than to venture so great a Leap in the dark, with a Lye in his mouth. If this man had been pardoned on the Scaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold after this Confession made, there want not some of that good nature, as to have stampt the Character of a <hi>Sham Plot</hi> upon the whole Affair, and to have turned it into ridicule, as they do every thing else that reflects up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on their Party.</p>
            <p>Good God! What a dismal Character must a <hi>certain Great Prince</hi> in <hi>Europe</hi> carry with him to Posterity! And how many indelible Blots must stick to the Escutcheon of his Triumphs! Those <hi>Illustrious Villains of Antiquity,</hi> that have Eternized their Names by turning the world up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>side down, and who have written their own Epitaphs in Letters of Blood and Horror, they may be reckoned but <hi>ill by halves,</hi> if compared with <hi>their Rivals of this Age.</hi> If it be any satisfaction to the miserable Inhabitants of the Shades below, not to have done on earth all the ill they might have done; then sure <hi>Attila,</hi> and the rest of those barbarous Heroes that over-ran the <hi>Roman</hi> Empire, may have something to value themselves upon, for not being altogether so cruel as some of their Successors have been.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Goths</hi> and <hi>Vandals</hi> broke out of those Bounds that Nature seemed at first to have set them; and carried Fire and Sword to Countries to which they had no imaginable Pretensions: These Scourges of mankind laid in Ashes the superbest Edifices and fruitfullest Territories of the then known world; and this merely to satisfie an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quenchable Thirst after Conquest. In all which, a Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bouring Nation has imitated them in the Age we live in, and the Copy has at last surpassed the Original. Let us search back into all the Histories that are lest us, of those mighty Irruptions of Barbarous Nations, upon the then Civilized Parts of the World, and we shall not find one
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:99113:4"/> single Vestige of a Baseness among them, equal to that which is the Subject of this Paper. Where, or whenever was it, that the <hi>Goths, Vandals,</hi> or <hi>Hunns,</hi> employed <hi>Assassinates</hi> to cut off by Steel or Poyson, any of the Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerals that came, or of the Princes that sent them, to op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose the Torrent of their Arms? All the Dangers their Enemies had to encounter with, were the ordinary Chances of War; and it was only in the Field of Battel that they ran any Hazard. This new way of making War among Princes, by suborning <hi>Ruffians</hi> to Assassinate an Enemy in cold blood, was reserved to the Age we live in, and to the memorable Reign of <hi>Lewis</hi> the XIVth. and it has obliged the World with a <hi>New</hi> Aera <hi>of Time,</hi> which may be named by those which come after us, <hi>The Age wherein Assassinations came first to be in use among Princes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>They deserved to be reckoned among the unthinking Croud, or were strangely blinded with prejudice, that have not observed a surprizing chain of happy Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dences, that encircled these Three Nations all along, since the late Revolution; so that our Preservation from time to time, may be esteemed the peculiar Care of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, in spight of our own Follies, and of our Enemies Malice. In every Scene that has opened to us these Four years past, there has been imprinted such unusual Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racters of the Divine Care to support this Government, as upon serious reflection, may put both Atheists and Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies to the blush. In short; if it were proper here to enlarge upon this subject, it might easily be made appear beyond contradiction, <hi>That the best-laid Contrivances of our Enemies abroad, the Intelligences given them by those at home, our own mistakes, the many seeming cros<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ness of Winds, Weather, and Tides, with many other odd accidents, have all of them concurred together, one step after another, to our Preservation.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:99113:5"/>
            <p>Our late <hi>Victory at Sea,</hi> was an astonishing Instance of this: <hi>A Victory, the best timed, the nearest to have escap'd us, and of the greatest consequences, all things considered, that ever this Nation had; and a Victory, in fine, that at one blow defeated all those vast Designs of our Enemies, that were just upon the breaking in upon us, and secured to us our own Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey, and the Dominion of the Seas.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Yet even this mighty <hi>Action</hi> was attended with such ir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>resistible strokes of the Divine Watchfulness and Care, that every Turning of the Tide, every Change of Wind, and every Storm at Sea for the space of six weeks together, did co-operate to our Successes. I shall never forget what the Gentleman that had as well <hi>the chief Glory</hi> as <hi>Command</hi> in that Action, was pleased to tell me a few days after it happened; <hi>That above Twenty different Accidents, all of them out of the Power of man, or the Sphere of his Designs, did concur to the obtaining that Victory; of which, the want of any one of them had unavoidably lost us the Opportunity.</hi> Adding, <hi>That every Change of Wind and Tide, from the mouth of the River to the place of Battel, seemed as designed by Heaven to concert the meeting of the two Fleets at that very critical moment they happened to meet; and which was yet the more remarkable, If they had not fought that very day, they had not fought at all, the Orders for Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sieur</hi> Tourville<hi>'s returning to</hi> Brest, <hi>coming to him within a few hours after he was engaged.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But of all the benign Providences that has attended these Nations these Four years past, none carries more re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>markable Characters in it, than the reiterated Preservati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of His Majesties Person, amidst the many <hi>open Dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers,</hi> and <hi>secret Practises</hi> he has been exposed to. One might think his Enemies had but little reason to put their Invention on the wrack how to carry him off by secret and indirect means, considering how familiar the greater Engines of Death are to him every day; and how un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weariedly
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:99113:5"/> he courts all Occasions to meet them in the Field. But this illustrious Life is too mighty <hi>an Obstacle to the Designs of the</hi> French <hi>King,</hi> (as Monsieur <hi>Grandvall</hi> expresses it) to allow his Enemies any satisfaction to see it exposed in every Rencounter to the fury of Cannon, and arm'd Battalions, unless to those they add <hi>Ignoble At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempts to take it away by the hand of a Ruffi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n.</hi> As the <hi>French</hi> King's sondness of his own Life denies his Enemies the hope that <hi>he shall one day descend into battel, and perish,</hi> (which was the foretold Fate of a King much of his own stamp) and by so doing, give that Peace to <hi>Europe</hi> in dying, which he never suffer'd it to enjoy while alive; So that boundless intrepidity of the King of <hi>England</hi> which gives us the greatest fears, one would think might give him some hope, since he sees never Prince bids fairer every day <hi>for Death or Victory.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Conduct of the late <hi>Cardinal Mazarine</hi> deserves admiration in all respects: But the Measures he observed himself, and left to his Master at his death, with refe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence to the Family of <hi>Orange,</hi> seems to have proceeded from <hi>a wonderful foresight,</hi> that nothing then in being could naturally lead him to. It was the Young Prince of <hi>Orange,</hi> now King of <hi>England,</hi> then under the Lowest Circumstances of his Fortunes, and at a time when no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing could be expected to make them better, but a Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racle; that this great <hi>Polititian</hi> employed a vast share of his Thoughts <hi>to keep him low,</hi> and to strengthen and soment a Faction that had made him so. During the first year of his Ministry, the Family of <hi>Orange,</hi> it is true, was in a Condition to give Jealousie to the Court of <hi>France</hi> in the person of a <hi>brave designing Prince,</hi> who was not only in possession of all the Places his Ancestors had enjoyed in a mighty Commonwealth, but was placed near the lustre of a Crown, by marrying a <hi>Daughter of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:99113:6"/>
            <p>But this <hi>Rising-Sun</hi> was soon set, and death put a stop to his Hereditary thirst of Glory in the very beginning of his career, leaving a Son yet unborn to wrestle with the unkind Misfortunes of <hi>a sinking Family.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It was then indeed that the House of <hi>Nassaw</hi> deserved rather the Compassionate Regards of all the Princes of Christendom, than to be the Object of their Envy and Fear. Then it was that a Family which had eternized its Name by raising a great and rich Republick out of a small Plank of the <hi>Spanish</hi> Dominion, and under whom all the Nations of <hi>Europe</hi> came to learn the Art of War for an hundred years together, did undergo an Eclipse, and such an one, as in the opinion of all the World was to put an end for ever to its wonted lustre.</p>
            <p>He that will but be at the pains to consider the dismal Scene that ushered in the present King of <hi>England</hi> into the World, with all the mighty Bars that stood in his way to hinder him from ever making a figure in it worthy of his Ancestors; and at the same time will gather together <hi>all the rising Changes of Fortune he has since undergone; all the things he has done, is a doing, and like to do;</hi> must of necessity conclude, That either Providence has brought about all these Extraordinary Events <hi>to no purpose</hi> (which methinks is a thought unworthy of the Divine Goodness and Wisdom) or that the Prince, who is become such an astonishing Instance of the Care of Heaven, must be <hi>he that shall redeem Europe.</hi> He was brought into the World many weeks before his time, and nothing but mourning for the Father was to be seen in the place where the Son first saw light. A full Moon passed over before it could be almost said he lived, and every minute for se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Months together was expected by all about him to be his last.</p>
            <p>By his Father's untimely death, and the heat of a prevailing Party in <hi>Holland,</hi> he came into the World de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spoiled
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:99113:6"/> of all the great Offices and Power his Ancestors had born in that State; and the Royal House of <hi>England,</hi> whose Blood mixed so near with his own, was likewise sunk with the Monarchy it self. Under these unpromi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing Circumstances of Fortune, did the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> draw his first breath; and the same unlucky Scene that ushered him in, continued to bear him company till the Two and twentieth year of his Age, when Heaven rais<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed him up in a moment, and by such surprising Steps, that after Ages will hardly believe, <hi>To put a full stop to a Conquering Enemy that had brought his Country to the brink of Ruin; and at the Age he could scarce write Man, to deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver that Commonwealth from the jaws of destruction.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What other astonishing greatness this Prince has risen to since, has already reached the Four parts of the habita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble World, and it's in him that in this Juncture <hi>all the Designs a-foot, for vindicating the Liberty of</hi> Europe, <hi>do Center.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It's hard to say, whether this Greatness of the King's be more pleasing to the rest of Christendom, than it's displea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing to <hi>France:</hi> This is certain, That they look upon him <hi>as the only Obstacle to the Designs of the</hi> French <hi>King; and that upon his death the Confederacy would break, and the</hi> French <hi>King would render himself Master;</hi> to give it in Monsieur <hi>Grandvall</hi>'s own precise words. This has put the Ministers of <hi>France</hi> upon a Design that must render their Memory infamous to all Ages, and of which their Master must expect to have a share.</p>
            <p>The Design in short was this. <hi>Monsieur</hi> de Louvois, <hi>the late Chief Minister of the</hi> French <hi>King, had concerted with Collonel</hi> Parker <hi>and one</hi> Dumont, <hi>to assassinate His Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jesty; but when, and after what manner it was to be done, is not yet made publick. Monsieur</hi> de Louvois <hi>dying, his Son Monsieur</hi> Barbesieux <hi>succeeds to his place, to his Credit
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:99113:7"/> with the King, and to the inglorious Design against the King of</hi> England<hi>'s Life, the plan of which his Father had left him in writing sealed up in his Cabinet. The new Minister, to accomplish a Villany his Father's death had rendered at first abor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive, employs in it Monsieur</hi> Grandvall, <hi>in conjunction with</hi> Dumont <hi>and</hi> Parker; <hi>promises by</hi> Grandvall <hi>to</hi> Dumont 20000 <hi>Livres of Estate, and a Knighthood of St.</hi> Lazar; <hi>and to</hi> Grandvall <hi>himself to make him a Duke, and to give him an Estate proportionable in case the blow succeeded; and all four, with Monsieur</hi> Paparell, <hi>Paymaster General to the</hi> French <hi>King's Army, and Madam</hi> Maintenon, <hi>the</hi> French <hi>King's she Favourite and Counsellor, do agree together the manner in which the Assassination should be done,</hi> viz. <hi>That</hi> Dumont, <hi>after having entred himself into the Confederate Army, should take his opportunity when His Majesty went to visit the grand Guard, or the Lines, to shoot him behind his back, and thereupon make the best of his way to a body of Horse</hi> Grandvall <hi>and</hi> Parker <hi>should have in readiness upon a previ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous intimation to rescue and carry him off. Thus prepared, and thus encouraged, the three Champions of Villany part from</hi> Paris, Dumont <hi>for the Confederate Army, and</hi> Parker <hi>and</hi> Grandvall <hi>to that commanded by Monsieur</hi> De Luxem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burgh. <hi>The two last wait with impatience at the Grand Guard night and day,</hi> (to give it in <hi>Grandvall</hi>'s own words, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the <hi>French</hi> Coppy) <hi>to hear from</hi> Dumont; and doubtless the Court of <hi>France</hi> waited with the same impatience every moment for the arrival of the Courier with the long-wished for News of the fatal Blow.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Heaven took care of the preservation of</hi> Europe, <hi>that did depend so visibly upon one single Life; And whether</hi> Dumont<hi>'s heart failed him, or whatever else was the cause, after some weeks attendance without being able to effectuate his Design, he retires to the Court of</hi> Hanover, <hi>and thus the Year</hi> 1691. <hi>pas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses over without a Red Letter in the Calender to denote the murther of a King. This Disappointment had no other in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluence
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:99113:7"/> on the</hi> French <hi>Court, than to set them on with the more eagerness to prosecute this Campagne,</hi> 1692. <hi>that, in which they had failed the year before.</hi> Grandvall <hi>and</hi> Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker <hi>returned to</hi> Paris, <hi>and are again set on work by</hi> Barbesieux <hi>and the rest of the Cabal, among whom Monsieur</hi> Chandlais, <hi>Quarter-master General to the</hi> French <hi>King, comes now first to appear; and Monsieur</hi> Leisdale, <hi>formerly employed in the States Service, is acquainted with the Design, and seems to go into it:</hi> Grandvall <hi>continues to keep Correspondence by Letters with</hi> Dumont, <hi>and</hi> Dumont <hi>with him and</hi> Barbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sieux <hi>both, by means of</hi> Dumont<hi>'s Wife at</hi> Paris. <hi>In the end, the Assassination is again resolved upon,</hi> Dumont <hi>is to perpetrate it, Monsieur</hi> Chandlais <hi>is in person to assist</hi> Grand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vall <hi>to rescue</hi> Dumont <hi>upon his doing it; and in order to the whole, a Rendezvouz is appointed at</hi> Uden <hi>between</hi> Grand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vall, Leisdale <hi>and</hi> Dumont, <hi>whither</hi> Dumont <hi>was to come from</hi> Hanover, <hi>and the other two from</hi> Paris: Parker <hi>at the same time coming for</hi> England, <hi>and they for</hi> Flanders; <hi>after all the three having taken leave of an unfortunate Prince at St.</hi> Germains, <hi>where they received from him all the Encouragements that was in his power to promise them in the hearing of the</hi> Italian <hi>Queen,</hi> who per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps would have Miscarried, if such a Crime, so suitable to her Genius and Country had been carried on without her having a share in it: and who, no doubt, hoped to succeed better in this than she had done in <hi>Jones</hi>'s, whom she had sent over to <hi>Ireland</hi> two years ago upon the like errand.</p>
            <p>The whole <hi>Plan</hi> being thus ready for Execution, Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven once more warded off the Blow by <hi>Leifdale</hi> and <hi>Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mont</hi>'s Discovery about one and the same time, and by the taking of <hi>Grandvall</hi> in his way to <hi>Ʋden;</hi> and thus the Court of <hi>France</hi> failed in their inglorious At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt to take away the Life of a Crowned Head by the Hand of a suborn'd Ruffian. Upon all which I shall
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:99113:8"/> confine my Reflections to a sew Heads, and that with all the respect that may be possibly due to two Persons of <hi>the first Rank among men,</hi> that have stained the lustre of their Birth with so <hi>fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l an Action.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What a horrid aspect the Crime of an <hi>Assassination</hi> car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries with it among all the Civilized Nations of the World, the common Consent of Mankind puts out of doubt: It may fall out, and indeed but very seldom, and p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rhaps not twice in the Revolution of a great many years, at least in these Climates, and at this distance from <hi>the Infal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lible Chair,</hi> that such a base kind of Revenge may come to lodge it self in the breast of some one <hi>noted Miscreant,</hi> who has thrown off all the common impressions of Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manity, and whose thread of life bespeaks him a <hi>Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster in H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>man shape,</hi> or a <hi>Prodigy of Wickedness.</hi> None else but such a Creature as this, will be found among the innumerable Ranks of men capable of so black a Crime; and when any such dismal Accident falls out in the World, we look upon it with the same horror and amaze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, that we do upon the <hi>most frightful excentrical Phoeno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mena's in Nature:</hi> The Perpetrator of this kind of Villa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny falls not only unlamented, but Death it self, that buries our resentment of most of other Crimes, is not able to protect him from our Execrations even in his Crave. If we look back to the few Attempts of this nature noted down to us in History (and but few they are) we shall find they went no further for the most part than the breast <hi>of one single Villain;</hi> and if at any time Accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plices were brought in, they were but one or two at most; so rare a thing it is to meet with any numbers of men together of that Diabolical Temper.</p>
            <p>But, good God! how fertile is the Court of <hi>France</hi> of this monstrous species of man! Instead of one or two per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons capable of so foul a Design, they can make up the number of <hi>Thirteen,</hi> at one dash. A baseness of this na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:99113:8"/> used in former Ages to lodge only with some of the lower herd of Mankind, who have little else to distinguish them outwardly from Bruits, but the shape: But here we have men <hi>of the first Quality among Subjects, of noble B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rth, of a lib<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ral Education, and in the greatest Posts in the Government of their Country: M ns<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>r</hi> Louvois <hi>and</hi> Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>besieux <hi>first Ministers of State, and the close Confidents of all their Master's Designs and S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>crets; Mons<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ur</hi> De Luxem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burgh, <hi>Duke, Peer and Marshall of</hi> France, <hi>the First Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mander of the</hi> French <hi>King's Armies, and by his Mother, of the Noblest Blood in</hi> Christendom <hi>that wears not a Crown; Monsieur</hi> Rabenack, <hi>and</hi> Bidall, <hi>both employed in the most dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficult Embassies; Monsieur</hi> Paparell <hi>and</hi> Chanlais, <hi>in the greatest Employments in the Army; and Madam</hi> Maintenon, <hi>though of no Quality, neither by her own birth, nor by her for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Husband, yet of nearest access of all Mortals to the</hi> French <hi>King's Person.</hi> These, and no meaner People, do stoop to so low and ignoble a Plot, <hi>when it makes for the Glory, or for the Interest of their Master;</hi> And which I would willingly bury in silence, Its not only they, but others <hi>of a yet more elevated Rank among men,</hi> that have thrown off all sense of Honour and Humanity, to come into it.</p>
            <p>If the assassinating of a private person carries with it such an horrid Idea, How much does that of a Prince, and set on by Princes? The greater the Persons be that either contrive, or against whom the Contrivance is made, still the greater is the Villany; And how far the Ministers of <hi>France</hi> may <hi>alone</hi> lie under the weight of so great an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>famy, may be worthy our inquiry.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The <hi>French</hi> King had all the reason in the World <hi>to stand behind the Curtain</hi> when such Engines were a playing, and not to appear barefaced on so foul a Stage. If Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sieur <hi>Barb<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>sieux</hi> thought it not sit to venture to <hi>speak to</hi> Dumont <hi>himself, for fear his Reputatation might suffer in
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:99113:9"/> case the Assassinat were seized</hi> (as <hi>Grandvall</hi> has told us) how much more reason had his Master to be cautious in so nice a point? There is a common <hi>decorum</hi> that He has not yet thought fit to throw off, with reference to Enemies of His Majesty's Rank; and he that above all Mortals is most in love with every shew of Glory, had been the weakest person alive, if he had neglected all possible Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumspection in this Affair.</p>
            <p n="2">2. But <hi>secondly,</hi> There was not the least Temptation or necessity for him to appear either to <hi>Grandvall, Dumont,</hi> or <hi>Leifdale,</hi> (who were the only persons that have been examined) or indeed to any one of the Conspirators, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept <hi>Barbesieux.</hi> No body in their right-wits will open themselves in so cursed a Design as this was, any further than as absolute necessity obliges them: And here it was enough that <hi>Barbesieux,</hi> his first Minister, <hi>received the Proposals, concerted the Matter, and promised Rewards.</hi> There are Cases every day in all the Courts of <hi>Europe,</hi> wherein <hi>Ministers</hi> treat with Spies, and such like men; and do both give and promise Rewards to them without their Master's appearing in it: How much rather in any business of so tender a nature, and in a Court where the <hi>first Minister</hi> is known to be intrusted with the greatest Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards, and the most uncontrolled Power in disposing of them?</p>
            <p n="3">3. It was sufficient to concert and set a foot the whole Design, that Monsieur <hi>Barb<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>sieux</hi> treated immediatly with <hi>Grandvall,</hi> and by him mediately with <hi>Dumont. Barbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sieux</hi> refused to treat personally with <hi>Dumont,</hi> for fear of his Reputation in case he was seized; that part being committed by him to <hi>Grandvall.</hi> So that whatever came of <hi>Dumont,</hi> who was to have the greatest part, if not all the hazard, <hi>Barbesieux</hi> thought his Honour safe, as never having spoken to him about it, and having <hi>Grandvall</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terposed betwixt them. Was it not as reasonable then,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:99113:9"/> that whoever put <hi>Barbesieux</hi> upon the Design, and gave him <hi>Orders</hi> or <hi>Leave</hi> to prosecute it, should use the same method as to all the rest of the Conspirators, except <hi>Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>besieux,</hi> as <hi>Barbesieux</hi> was to do with them all, but <hi>Grand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vall, To discover himself to none, but to him to whom he must of necessity do it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. Whoever reflects upon the Train of the late Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sieur <hi>Louvois</hi> Life and Actions, will not be able to trace any Vestage of so much ill nature and baseness, as was necessary to put him originally on so b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ack a Design. He had acquired, during the whole course of his Ministry, the Character of a man of some Honour; and was known to have endeavoured what in him lay, to mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate the violent courses of the Court; and particularly with relation to the Protestants, in which matter he and the late Chancellor his Father, had some Differences that could not be kept secret. So that all the harsh measures that Monsieur <hi>Louvois</hi> went into, were look'd upon as the effect of his Compliance with his Master's Temper and Inclinations, and not of his own Ill Nature. To in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stance this in one particular; When that unparallel'd Edict was in Agitation in the Council, <hi>Forbidding all the Protestant Women to be brought to bed by any but Roman-Catholick Midwives, Louvois</hi> appeared against it; and no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing could bring him to change his mind, but his Master's rising up with his <hi>Je le voux;</hi> after which, there was no more debating. Monsieur <hi>de Louvois</hi> being then a Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man of no ill disposition, it's both unjust and unreasonable to think he could be brought into a Conspiracy to Murder a Crowned Head, tho never so much an Enemy to <hi>France,</hi> out of any other Principle, than that of a desire to please and obey him on whom his Fortune depended; and every body knows that that Favourite saw no body in <hi>France</hi> greater than himself, except his Master.</p>
            <pb n="14" facs="tcp:99113:10"/>
            <p>But 5. Can it enter into any reasonable man's thoughts, that Monsieur <hi>Barb<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>sieux</hi> could be <hi>the original spring of the Motion</hi> after his Father's Death? Who knows not that <hi>Barbesieux</hi> is both a very young Man, and a young Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster, and one that is rather in the Quality of a Clerk or Privado to the <hi>French</hi> King, than a Counsellor, tho trusted with his Secrets? And indeed he is the <hi>Favourite Minister</hi> rather for his Father's sake, who was one of the best Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants ever Prince had, than for any merit he has yet acquired of his own.</p>
            <p n="6">6. It's not to be imagined that either <hi>Louvois</hi> or <hi>Barbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sieux</hi> durst have ventured on such an action, without an higher command; since whatever should come of it, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the Blow given, and the Assassinates come off, or ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken and put to the Rack, it must have necessarily come to be discovered who <hi>set them on;</hi> and thereby they two must have ventured their Court with the King, if not their Heads; since he would be obliged, for the common rules of Decency used among Princes, <hi>to disown both the Action and them.</hi> Let us judge then, if men of or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary sense, or acquaintance with the world, would have embarqued themselves in <hi>so hazardous a bottom,</hi> unless they knew before-hand the Action would be so far relished by the Master, <hi>as they might be able to pin upon him th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Care of their Safety after it is done.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="7">7. Tho all I have said to this purpose carried no weight with it; yet the <hi>Great Monarch</hi> will not be believed, not to have been very deeply engaged in a business of so vast a concern, when it's found, that not only his <hi>First Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>st<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r of State,</hi> but the <hi>Chief Commander of his Armies</hi> are in it. In the common opinion of the world, founded up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on custom, Whatever a <hi>First Minister</hi> does in matters that concern the State, especially of so tender a nature as the Design in question is, he is presumed to do it by Consent, at least if not by the positive Command of his Master.
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:99113:10"/> This obtains every where, but more especially in the Court of <hi>France,</hi> where the <hi>Premier Minister</hi> does trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>act the greatest Affairs himself, and does write the King's Name to Orders of the greatest Consequence, both to Generals at Sea and Land, without the King's own Hand. So that an Order under the Minister's Hand, carries with it a natural supposition that he has consulted the King be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he Signs it; and thence it is, that it receives as pun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctual Obedience as if the King had Signed it himself. But notwithstanding this, the Power of the <hi>Premier Minister</hi> has its own boun<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s, that every man in the Government knows how far it goes. And none employed in this Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spiracy could be so silly, as to believe <hi>Barbesieux</hi> had power of himself to promise <hi>Grandvall</hi> to <hi>make him a Duke, or to give him an Estate proportionable.</hi> Rewards and Honours of so high a nature, are only in the King's own breast to give; and except the King knew of it, we must suppose that <hi>Barbesieux</hi> and <hi>Grandvall</hi> were not only Knaves, but Fools, the one to promise, and the other to expect them.</p>
            <p n="8">8 There is another Reflection to this purpose, which I am willing to mention with all the tenderness due to a Crowned Head. The <hi>French</hi> King has acquired to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self by a great many actions, the unlucky Character of a Prince <hi>that makes no difficulty to step over all Laws Divine or Human, when it makes for his Glory or Interest.</hi> His be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haviour towards his Protestant Subjects, in spight of Fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damental Laws, and solemn reiterated Oaths to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary; his Swearing to so many Treaties of Peace with his Neighbouring Princes and States, and breaking them almost as soon as sworn; or rather, <hi>his swearing them with a design to be the better able to break them,</hi> do bear so ill a, face, as may make all the Nations about conclude, That a Design <hi>which should oblige the Confederate Princes to recal each of them their Troops out of</hi> Flanders, <hi>and by which</hi> Flan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:99113:11"/>
               <hi>being left without Soldiers, the</hi> French <hi>King might make himself Master of it, and the late King</hi> James <hi>be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stored,</hi> (to give it in Monsieur <hi>Grandvall</hi>'s own words), carried with it such forcible Temptations as was not in his power to resist.</p>
            <p n="9">9. Madam <hi>Maintenon</hi>'s part in this Aff ir, affords a shrewd suspicion against her great Benefactor. This Wo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>man, from being the Wife of a <hi>poor, deformed, Barlesque Poet,</hi> has risen to one of the First Places of Confidence about the <hi>French</hi> King. If there were any such thing in nature as <hi>Charms</hi> or <hi>Filtres</hi> to incite Love, it's to the se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret force of them, that thousands in <hi>France</hi> would be apt to impute this unaccountable Friendship and Intimacy betwixt <hi>Scarron</hi>'s Widow, and <hi>Le vis</hi> the XIVth. It were hard to assign any other cause that should oblige the Proudest Monarch upon earth to lay aside all his Glory and Pomp, to lock up himself above four hours every day in the closest Conversation with a Creature, that is now Mistress of no other Charms but that of <hi>Wit.</hi> No mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal has more frequent or nearer opportunities to know his Genius and Temper; and every body will allow her more sense than to embark in so nice a business, without she knew before-hand, that it would please him; nor is it to be dreamed that she has so little Zeal to preserve herself in his favour, as to venture upon that which she might easi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y think would oblige the <hi>French</hi> King, if he himself were innocent, to sacrifice her to his Honour. And in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, not only she, but the rest must be accounted down<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right Fools, if they had ventured upon this Conspiracy, without a natural foresight, that unless they had their Master's Approbation, they might come to run the fate of the <hi>Amalekite that brought to</hi> David <hi>the Head of his mortal Enemy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And this leads me to one Reflection more, that must certainly cast the scale, in the opinion of all unbiassed
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:99113:11"/> people, and which I doubt not, but at this very day, <hi>is the determining Point that all</hi> Europe <hi>has in their view with respect to this Affair.</hi> Here, we see, are concerned two persons of the nearest access to the <hi>French</hi> King, and in his closest Confidence, Monsieur <hi>Barbesieux,</hi> and Madam <hi>Maintenon;</hi> here is concerned his greatest General, on whom he has laid the weight of his Fortune in this War, the Duke of <hi>Luxemburgh;</hi> and here are other two per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons of considerable figure in his Army, <hi>Paparell</hi> and <hi>Chanlais;</hi> and to bring up the Reer, here are two persons employed in his Embassies abroad, <hi>Bedall</hi> and <hi>Rabenack:</hi> It's in the face of the Sun, and to the Conviction of all <hi>Christendom,</hi> that all these persons are proved to have ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naged a Conspiracy <hi>to Murther the King of</hi> England: Now if the <hi>French</hi> King knows himself to have had no In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluence on this Affair, we are certainly to expect that by this time they are in <hi>the last Disgrace with their Master;</hi> and that for tainting his Service with so black a Crime, contrary to the Law of Nations, and all rules usual among Princes, <hi>they are, at least, for ever banished</hi> France. There is no other means left now but this, to persuade the world of the <hi>French</hi> King's Innocence: But if at any time hereafter, we find that all these Persons, or any of them, are continued in their wonted Favour and Employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, then all the Nations of <hi>Christendom</hi> will take leave to conclude, <hi>That these Conspirators did no more but Comply with the Commands of one they durst not Disobey.</hi> And that herein there is no hardship put upon the <hi>French</hi> King, I appeal to all the Princes of <hi>Europe,</hi> Whether or not, in case any of their <hi>Ministers</hi> were found to Conspire the Murder of another Prince, tho never so much their Enemy, they would not inflict at least that Punishment which we may well make the Test of the <hi>French</hi> King's Innocency in this Plot of the Marquis of <hi>Barbesieux.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="18" facs="tcp:99113:12"/>
            <p>To sum up this Enquiry, it's worth observing, That in the Printed Account there are a great many things re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lating to this Conspiracy omitted, which his Majesty, for some Reasons of State, or perhaps out of a Principle of inimitable Generosity, has thought fit not to make pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick: For in the <hi>French</hi> Copy it's said, with respect to the Circumstances of that design, <hi>On n' en mettra pour tant que tres peu jey; Of which we shall mention but a very few here.</hi> This Intimation is given us when it comes to mention <hi>Leefdale</hi>'s Deposition; and it is not to be doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, but this Gentleman being heartily resolved all along to discover the Villany, he would omit no occasion to pump out all that possibly he could learn, relating thereto, in his Conversation with the Conspirators. So that whatever Provocations and Personal Injuries the <hi>French</hi> King has done His Majestly, it seems a Greatness of Mind forbids Him to expose His Enemy all he can.</p>
            <p>Leaving the <hi>French</hi> King to wash off from himself, the best way he can, the Blot that must stick to his Memory in this Horrid Attempt, I can't omit to add to this, some remarkable Passages, never hitherto made publick; by which the world may see the Temper of our King, and the Unjustness and Ingratitude of some of his Enemies.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>About Ten years ago he received a Letter from an unknown hand, who yet gave himself a Name, in which he offered to deliver</hi> Europe <hi>from all her Fears, by destroying the</hi> French <hi>King; he desired only a safe Refuge in</hi> Holland, <hi>and a small Subsistence, much less than he should leave behind him in</hi> France: <hi>He desired an Answer might be writ to him, and left with the Post-master's Wife at</hi> Paris. <hi>And about a week after, he writ a second to the same purpose. The first Letter came to the then Prince of</hi> Orange <hi>at night, at</hi> Loo, <hi>and Monsieur</hi> Dykvelt <hi>happened to be with him; so he shewed him the Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and desired him to go to the</hi> Hague <hi>immediately, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver that Letter to Monsieur</hi> D' Avaux, <hi>who was then the</hi>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:99113:12"/> French <hi>Ambassador to the</hi> States: <hi>Monsieur</hi> Dykvelt <hi>made such haste, that he was with Monsieur</hi> D' Avaux <hi>next morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and gave him the Letter (and the second was likewise sent to him): He received it with great Acknowledgments of the Prince's Generosity, and sent the Letter to</hi> Paris. <hi>The Post-master's Wife being examined, said, That one had come several times to call for a Letter; but he not coming again, she was ordered to go about</hi> Paris, <hi>and see if she could know him again: One was taken up, who she believed was the person, and was put in the</hi> Bastile; <hi>he happened to be a Protestant, which no doubt made the Court of</hi> France <hi>to like the Discovery the better: But when some of the Parliament came to examine him, and to Confront him with the woman, she, when she view<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed him nearly, and heard him speak, owned that she was mista<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, and that he was not the man; so after a little while, he was dismiss'd, and came into</hi> Holland <hi>upon the general Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>secution of the Protestants.</hi> By these Circumstances it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears, That the Court of <hi>France</hi> believed that this was a <hi>Real Design,</hi> and no Contrivance thrown out to try the Prince's Temper. But another Instantce shewed, that the King looks on Propositions of this kind, with so much horror, that he thought that which on all other occasions was the most Sacred with him, I mean <hi>His Word,</hi> did not bind in this. <hi>A few days after the King came to the Crown, an unknown person writ to the L. B. of S. That he had a Proposition of great Consequence to make to the King, if he should have his Promise, That he might do it safely. This the King allowed the Bishop to do; so he writ to him by the name and method that he had given: When he came to him, he told how long he had lived and served in</hi> Versailles, <hi>and how well he knew all the method of that Court; and at last he came to offer to kill the</hi> French <hi>King: At this the Bishop started up im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately, and said, He thought the King was too well-known, for any to dare to come with such a Proposition; he hoped he himself had been also so well known, that none should have made
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:99113:13"/> it by him; he was sorry that a Promise was given of Safety; but he bid the Rogue be gone immediately. When he gave an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of this, next day, the King thought he had carried the matter of the Promise too far; for no Promise was to be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstood to relate to such Crimes; and therefore he wished that the Bishop had seized on him; and ordered him to be sure to do it, if ever he could set eye on him again.</hi> But since this is so noble a Head, and so suitable to the Cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage, as well as to the other great and truly Royal Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities of our Glorious King, I will give some more In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stances, which shew how little he deserved of the Late King, that he should encourage so black an Action. <hi>When he came first into</hi> England, <hi>he understood as he came along, that some began to talk of proceeding against King</hi> James<hi>'s Person, and he desired him that acquainted him with this, to find out who they were that held such discourse, for he would suffer none of them to stay about him.</hi> And it appeared ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry evidently at <hi>Windsor,</hi> how firm he was to this Resolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; for when he had the late King in his hands, and that many advised him to keep him safe at least, till <hi>Ireland</hi> were reduced, if not to the end of the War; some proposing his own Town of <hi>Breda</hi> as a fit place: He said, <hi>Those Advices might be perhaps both wise and safe, but he could not follow them; for whatever he might do in the way of War, he could not bring himself to do any thing perso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally against him;</hi> and he not only gave the Guards that waited on him, Publick Orders, but Secret Directions to leave him at full liberty, as appeared by the Event. Ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Instance will shew, not only how far the King is from the possibility of hearkning to all black Propositions, but even to Indirect ones, when the Persons of Princes may be endangered by them. <hi>When the late King was in</hi> Ireland, <hi>a Proposition was made by one that had served him, and loved him, that he thought might put an end to the War. He sent it to the King by the B. of S. it was this: He moved,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:99113:13"/> That a Third Rate Ship well manned, and well commanded, might be sent to St.</hi> George's <hi>Channel; and that when they should come near</hi> Dublin, <hi>they should have Orders to declare for the late King; and send him a Message about it, which he who made the motion, and that was to go along in the Ship, said he would be one of those that should carry it. He did not doubt but that upon the Invitation, King</hi> James <hi>would presently come aboard, and then they should sail away with him; but he added two things, the one was, That they should have Orders not to bring him to</hi> England, <hi>or to make him a Prisoner, but to carry him either to some part of</hi> Spain <hi>or</hi> Italy, <hi>and there to set him ashore; the other was, That he should have Ten thousand Guineas consigned in the Ship to be given to him in the place where they should land him, that so he might not be in too naked a condition. When the King, heard all this, he said it looked plausible, and he verily believed it would take; but with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out taking time to think on it, he said he would not meddle with it. He hated Tricks, and would be in none: Besides, the late King, if he came aboard, would bring some of his Guards with him, who without doubt would offer at some resistance, when they saw themselves catched; upon that a disorder might arise, and some of the Sea-men might perhaps knock King</hi> James <hi>in the head; therefore he would go on in a fair open way, and trust to the Providence of God, while he maintained his Integrity.</hi> These Instances will shew in how different a mould the King was cast, from those who can either contrive or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courage the detestable Practise that is now by the good Providence of God discovered.</p>
            <p>But to the Conspiracy it self. How far it went before Monsieur <hi>de Louvois</hi>'s death, we know no more by the printed Account, <hi>than that it was concerted, and that</hi> Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mont <hi>was to be employed in it.</hi> But there are undoubted grounds to believe it has been of an old date, and that more were concerned in it than Monsieur <hi>de Louvois</hi> and <hi>Dumont.</hi> That there was one <hi>Jones</hi> employed to mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:99113:14"/> the King, both <hi>here,</hi> before His Majesty went to <hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> and when he was there, the intercepted Letter of <hi>Tyrconnell</hi> to the late Queen, and a Journal of other Letters found at <hi>Dublin</hi> in a <hi>certain Closet,</hi> leaves us no ground to doubt. The most material steps that were made in it after <hi>Barbesieux</hi> came to the Ministry, the printed Rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is pretty clear and exact.</p>
            <p>In the whole management of this Affair, the <hi>French</hi> Court has shewed with a deep cunning the blackest Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chery against a Prince whom their King pretends to protect.</p>
            <p>The first and inmost wheel of this motion is not to be seen. The next is <hi>Barbesieux,</hi> and he appears not to <hi>Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mont,</hi> who is to give the blow, and to run the most apparent hazard of being seized, and brought to a Confession; but treats only with <hi>Grandvall,</hi> who is to share the least in the Danger, and is in less probability to be seized, and he alone is to treat with <hi>Dumont.</hi> Again, <hi>Barbesieux</hi> pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends to inform <hi>Grandvall</hi> of a personal Injury done him by the King, no less <hi>than the ordering his Father to be poison<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,</hi> for which he said he <hi>might now be revenged;</hi> and even to this he uses only the soft word, <hi>he suspects it.</hi> The reason of his pretending this, is only to cover the horror of the Design as to himself, with the notion of a personal Revenge for the murther of his Father; and uses no harsher word, than <hi>that he suspects it,</hi> to the end, that <hi>Grandvall</hi> might not lay so much stress upon that story, as to lessen the true motives he was to act upon, which <hi>Grandvall</hi> tells us himself, was, <hi>because His Majesty was look'd upon as the only Obstacle to the</hi> French <hi>King's Designs.</hi> As for the ridiculous Story it self, it were an officious piece of folly for any one to take further notice of it; The <hi>monopoly of poisoning</hi> is to be left to the <hi>French</hi> Court, that deserves it best, for the great improvements they have made of late years in that Art.</p>
            <pb n="23" facs="tcp:99113:14"/>
            <p>The <hi>French</hi> Court's management with regard to the Assassinate <hi>Dumont,</hi> is a continued thread of Craft, and the poor Wretch is cheated in the whole tract of it; he is to kill the King, and thereby run an almost inevitable hazard of being either killed on the place, or taken and hanged. But since no body will venture on such an Action without some hopes of getting off, they feed him with a fine project of <hi>having</hi> 1500 <hi>Horse the first year under the Command of</hi> Grandvall <hi>and</hi> Parker: <hi>and</hi> 3000 <hi>the next under Monsieur</hi> Chanlais <hi>himself to resque and bring him off.</hi> This is all stuff, and in the opinion of every bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy that understands any thing of War, was next to an im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>possibility: And it is strange that he could not see through it; but it seems the impression of 20000 <hi>Livres of Estate, and a Knighthood of St.</hi> Lazar, had intoxicated him so, as to shut up all the other Avenues of his Soul. The <hi>French</hi> Court made their account, that <hi>Dumont</hi> must be sacrificed, which is one of the reasons that <hi>Barbesieux</hi> uses so much caution with him; and <hi>Grandvall</hi> tells <hi>Leefdale</hi> plainly, That <hi>it little concerned them whether</hi> Dumont <hi>was taken or not.</hi> But this is not all; the miserable Creature is to be shamm'd out of his life, what way soever the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter went. Upon his succeeding in the Attempt, he must either happen to be seized, or to escape; if seized, he is sure to be hanged; if he escapes, and comes back for his Reward, it's not to be doubted but he was to be hanged likewise, <hi>and that merely to blind the World with a no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the</hi> French <hi>King's abhorrence of the Act; Dumont</hi> having nothing to shew for his Warrant, and <hi>Grandvall</hi> being the only person that had treated with him, and that was in no capacity to keep him harmless. It's true, We find <hi>that by means of his Wife,</hi> Dumont <hi>had sent several Letters to</hi> Barbesieux; but <hi>Barbesieux</hi> was better advised than to write him Answers himself, that being left to <hi>Grandvall</hi> to do: So that all along <hi>Barbesieux</hi> is safe for
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:99113:15"/> any thing that <hi>Dumont</hi> can say of <hi>his personal treating with him;</hi> and thus there is no imaginable way left for the As<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sassinate to escape the Gallows, whatever comes on it: for either he must be hanged, if taken by the Confederates; or if he escape their hands, he must be sacrificed to <hi>a piece of Pageantry of the</hi> French <hi>Court.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But the <hi>French</hi> Court, though they were resolved to sacrifice <hi>Dumont,</hi> they take all care possible he shall not fail in the Attempt: As they put him on the Action it self with the hopes of great Rewards, and of being re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scued and brought off, so they put him on to do it in the manner that was least likely to miss: They tell him a false story of the <hi>King's wearing a Coat of Mail;</hi> or rather, <hi>a Wastcoat of Mail under his Cloaths,</hi> as it's in the <hi>French</hi> Copy; and <hi>Barb<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>sieux</hi> is the person that invents this, and commands <hi>Grandvall</hi> to tell it to <hi>Damont:</hi> The reason of this story is, That <hi>Dumont</hi> might not betake himself to the <hi>Poynard,</hi> which they foresaw would be more difficult, as requiring nearer Access to His Majesties Person, and likewise was not so certainly mortal; but to let him see the necessity of using <hi>Fire-Arms,</hi> that kill at a greater di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stance, and surer. When in the mean time the <hi>French</hi> Court could not but know, That His Majesty does so far neglect all such pre-cautions as a Coat of Mail, that the Prayers of those about him could never prevail with him to part with, or so much as to cover his <hi>Blew Ribbon</hi> or <hi>Star</hi> in Action. There is yet another Artifice used with <hi>Dumont,</hi> to make sure of him. It was reasonable to sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose from his abandoning the Design the year before, and his retiring, to the Court of <hi>Hanouer,</hi> that he might enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain some scruples about the feasibleness of his being re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scued by persons of no greater Figure or Command, than <hi>Grandvall</hi> or <hi>Parker:</hi> Therefore it is agreed upon, that one in a greater Post, and who is known in <hi>France</hi> to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cel in the Art of Taking up Ground for a Camp, or laying
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:99113:15"/> an Ambuscade, should now Command the Party that was to rescue him; <hi>and that instead of</hi> 1500 <hi>Horse, headed by</hi> Grandvall <hi>and</hi> Parker <hi>the year</hi> 1691, <hi>there should be</hi> 3000 <hi>employed to that purpose the year</hi> 1692, <hi>under the Command of Monsieur</hi> Chanlais.</p>
            <p>But the carriage of the <hi>French</hi> Court in this Affair, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the late King <hi>James,</hi> is a master-piece of Craft and Treachery. Here it is, that it were almost to be wish'd, that there were a Curtain drawn over that part of the Stage, <hi>where this Ʋnfortunate Prince comes to act so unnatu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral and so affrightful a part.</hi> That any one that ever fill'd the <hi>English</hi> Throne, should be capable of so Un-princely a Revenge as Murder, is a very mortifying Reflection, and leads us naturally to look back to <hi>some shrowdly-suspect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Events</hi> that have fallen out in <hi>England</hi> of late years, which for some Reasons are not now insisted on.</p>
            <p>As in most of the Transactions of this Prince's Reign, he was imposed upon by the <hi>French</hi> King's Designs, and gave himself up to the Measures given him from <hi>France,</hi> which proved his Ruin; so now, when under their Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection, they bring him in to cover and own a Transaction so base and horrid, that the <hi>French</hi> King had not the face to appear in it himself. They so ordered the matter, that Grandvall, Parker, <hi>and</hi> Leefdale, <hi>should wait upon King</hi> James, <hi>and receive his Approbation of the thing, with Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mises of Encouragement;</hi> and this is not done till the whole Design had been fully concerned before-hand. It was fit the Murder of the King should pass in the world as a Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sonal Revenge of King <hi>James,</hi> and that the <hi>French</hi> Court should lay it upon the Quarrel betwixt those two Princes, tho at the same time <hi>they had the chief hand in the Contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance of it, were to reward the Instruments employed in it, and were to reap the greatest Advantages by it.</hi> Whether that Unfortunate Prince was sensible of this Trick put upon him, or whether his eager desire to see the King ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:99113:16"/> off, gave him no leisure for Reflection, it's hard to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termine: This is clear, That he thought himself no ways obliged to use the precautions that even <hi>Barbesieux</hi> had done; since that after his speaking to <hi>Grandvall,</hi> accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the words in the printed account, <hi>he was pleased to entertain</hi> Parker, Leefdale, <hi>and him, all together on the same subject;</hi> for in the <hi>French</hi> Copy it's said, <hi>Qu' alors il a a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ssi p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rlè av<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>c le dit</hi> Parker <hi>&amp;</hi> Leefdale, <hi>de cette Affaire: At the same time H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> (meaning King <hi>James,</hi> and not the Prisoner <hi>Grandvall,</hi> as in the <hi>English</hi> Translation) <hi>spoke likewise to</hi> Parker <hi>and</hi> Leefdale <hi>about that Affair.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Treachery of the <hi>French</hi> Court towards King <hi>James</hi> in this business is <hi>deep</hi> and <hi>black:</hi> All the world lays his Ruin at the <hi>French</hi> King's door; and it's to the Measures he gave, him, that he owes the loss of Three Crowns: The least amends could be made him for all this, was an Honourable Retreat in <hi>France;</hi> yet that this is granted him only on the account of their own Interest, appears in a great many Instances, and particularly in the part they bring him in to act in this Conspiracy. If there had been true Friendship and Kindness meant him, they would never have put upon him a necessity of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king himself known in so foul a Design to <hi>Three persons all at once;</hi> but they would have at least allowed him the pre-cautions that <hi>Barbesieux,</hi> if not the very same that one of his <hi>own rank</hi> thought themselves obliged to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serve.</p>
            <p>But this is not all: In bringing King <hi>James</hi> to own this business, the <hi>French</hi> Court did him the last offices of an Enemy. Instead of promoting his Re-accession to the Throne, they did more at one dash to shut it for ever against him, than all that his Enemies could have thought of. With what horror must the <hi>English</hi> Nation have been struck, to see a Prince that had recovered them from the brink of Destruction, and exposed his Person so often
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:99113:16"/> for their sake; to see him, I say, murdered by the bloody hand of a Ruffian! And with what execrations and cries for Vengeance, against both Actors and Contrivers of such a Villany! Could the <hi>French</hi> ever imagine, that the way for King <hi>James</hi> to regain the hearts of the Three Kingdoms, that he had lost by his endeavouring the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>version of their Laws and Liberties, was <hi>to hire Three Parricides to murder the only Person that had secured these to them?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If the sight of <hi>Caesar</hi>'s <hi>Bloody Shirt</hi> had so wonderful an Influence on the <hi>Roman</hi> people, that <hi>Brutus</hi> and <hi>Cassias,</hi> his Murderers, whom the very day before they had honour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with the glorious names of <hi>Liberatores Patriae, The Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viours of their Countrey,</hi> were thereupon forced to fly <hi>Rome,</hi> and seek Sanctuary elsewhere from their Rage; what just Resentments would not the dismal news of <hi>our British Caesar</hi>'s <hi>Murder,</hi> and the sight of a Queen, <hi>and such a Queen,</hi> in Tears, have kindled in every <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lish</hi> breast, against the Perpetrators, Contrivers, and Abettors of so horrid and cursed a Crime?</p>
            <p>The case indeed is vastly different betwixt the <hi>Roman Caesar</hi> and <hi>ours:</hi> The Ancient Frame and Constitution of <hi>Rome</hi> was subverted by the one; and the restoring to <hi>England</hi> its first and best Constitution of Government, is who<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ly owing to the other. Let us judge then, if the Murder of <hi>Julius Caesar</hi> was so much resented by the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans,</hi> that nothing but the Blood of <hi>Brutus</hi> and <hi>Cassius,</hi> two men, otherwise Excellent, and once their Darlings, could appease their Wrath, and all this, <hi>because, tho</hi> Caesar <hi>had enslaved</hi> Rome, <hi>yet he was Brave and Virtuous?</hi> How much more deeply resented wou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d the Murder of a King have been, <hi>who instead of enslaving his own Countrey, had saved both It and Ours; and whose Bravery and Virtue is equally the Admiration and Envy of his Enemies;</hi> and this procured by a Prince whom we had but too many Reasons before <hi>not to love or wish for?</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="28" facs="tcp:99113:17"/>
            <p>Thanks to Heaven the Fatal Design has miscarried! but still the Guilt and Infamy remains: And we are ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the most insensible, or the maddest people that ever was, if this one action of the late King's, tho there were no more, don't stamp upon us an indelible impressi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <hi>of that dreadful condition we should fall into, if ever through the Anger of H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aven, or by our own Follies, we should come again under the Power of a Prince of this Temper, and capable of such Actions.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But how little regard the Conspirators had to King <hi>James</hi>'s Rewards or Interest, and for whose sake, and up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on whose Promises of Recompence it was they acted, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears evidently by their own Confession: <hi>It was</hi> 20000 <hi>Livres of Estate, and a Knighthood of St.</hi> Lazar, <hi>that</hi> Dumont, <hi>and it was a Dutchy that</hi> Grandvall <hi>expected;</hi> and none of all these in <hi>England,</hi> but in <hi>France,</hi> and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mised them by <hi>French</hi> Ministers. As their Rewards were to be in <hi>France,</hi> so the Motives which wrought upon them, were those which regard the <hi>French</hi> King and his Greatness; and for the Restoration of King <hi>James,</hi> that came in only by the by, and in consequence of the other. So then, tho the late King was as forward as any of the rest to come into the Conspiracy, yet it was upon the <hi>French</hi> King's Credit, and for his Interest alone, that both <hi>Grandvall</hi> and <hi>Dumont</hi> were persuaded to engage in the business.</p>
            <p>What further remains necessary to be taken notice of, with respect to this Conspiracy, shall be done in as few words as possible.</p>
            <p>We find that upon the Rumour spread of <hi>some Disor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders in</hi> Scotland <hi>which would oblige His Majesty to cross the Seas again, Grandvall</hi>'s patience was almost at an end, which puts him upon hastning <hi>Leefdale</hi> with this expressi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, <hi>Dear friend, we are like to lose our Fortune; I beg of you that we may go away immediately.</hi> He had swallowed a
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:99113:17"/>
               <hi>Dutchy</hi> already in his thoughts, and was impatient till he was put in possession of it, by succeeding in his Errand to <hi>Flanders;</hi> But his going into the Jesuits Colledge at <hi>Brussels</hi> on the road, to beg <hi>That God would bless their Ʋn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertaking,</hi> was, after all, a clear Demonstration, that one principal Motive that had been suggested to him to Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the King, was the <hi>account of Religion:</hi> For when was it heard, That an Assassinate, set on by a mere Perso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Revenge or Interest, had the Impudence to beg the Assistance of God Almighty to an Undertaking of that kind? This is a convincing Argument, that he thought God's Glory was concerned in an Attempt to take off a <hi>Heretick Prince that stood in the way of his Master's Designs.</hi> We know how far of late years the <hi>Court-Divines</hi> of <hi>France</hi> have carried their Casuistical Doctrine, to Patronize the very worst of Actions, where they tend to the Glory or Interest of the <hi>French</hi> King. In <hi>several of their Printed Theses</hi> they have positively asserted, <hi>That an Action in it self morally ill, becomes good, if the Intention be to serve the King, or extirpate Heresie.</hi> No wonder then, that a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son of <hi>Grandvall</hi>'s Temper, and embark'd in such an Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fair, should embrace a Notion of Divinity that might set his Conscience at ease in what then he was going about.</p>
            <p>In the printed Account we find Monsieur <hi>Maurau,</hi> En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voy from <hi>Poland</hi> to the States, is mentioned, <hi>as one that kept a close Correspondence with</hi> Bedell, <hi>and by his means with the Court of</hi> France; and are told, <hi>that by the help of these two, the</hi> French <hi>Court managed their choicest Correspon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence in</hi> Holland. It may not be altogether improper to give some hint what this <hi>Maurau</hi> is, and from thence we may observe the subtile management of the <hi>French</hi> Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters.</p>
            <p>This is a Man of extraordinary Parts, and an unbound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Ambition. He was formerly one of the Three <hi>extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary Provincial Treasurers of War in</hi> France, which
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:99113:18"/> place he kept about eight years together. In the year 1682. (if I mistake not) he was arrrested, together with <hi>Arnauld</hi> and <hi>Talon,</hi> his two Collegues, <hi>Pour avoir dever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tii une grande somme des aeniers du roy.</hi> In plain <hi>English, For having robbed the King of a vast sum of Money:</hi> All three were carried to <hi>Amiens</hi> in order to be tried for their Lives before Monsieur <hi>d' Bretuell</hi> the <hi>Intendant;</hi> but before they were brought to their Tryal, <hi>Arnauld</hi> prevented his Judges, <hi>by killing himself in Prison;</hi> the other two were found guilty, but at the Solicitation of Monsieur <hi>Louvois,</hi> whose Creatures they had been, they were only sentenced <hi>to be banished for ever the Kingdom of</hi> France, <hi>and to have all their Estates confiscated.</hi> Whereupon they retired into <hi>Holland,</hi> where some time thereafter, by the means of Monsieur <hi>Bethune,</hi> the Favourite of the Queen of <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, Maurau</hi> was made Envoy from that Crown to the <hi>States.</hi> Now, who could have imagined that a Man <hi>thus Banished, Ruined, and Affronted</hi> in <hi>France,</hi> should be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come one of the two Persons, <hi>that the</hi> French <hi>Court em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploy'd to manage their choicest Correspondence</hi> in <hi>Holland?</hi> This seemed yet the more improbable, because <hi>Maurau</hi> was noted for <hi>exclaiming in all Companies, and on all Occasions against the</hi> French <hi>King and his Actions;</hi> insomuch, that it was wondered at by every body, how a Man employed in an Ambassy from a Neutral Crown, came to shew so openly his inveterate hatred against <hi>France,</hi> without the least reserve of good manners.</p>
            <p>It appears now, that all was but a <hi>Sham</hi> to carry on with less Suspition his Intriegues with the <hi>Ministers</hi> of <hi>France.</hi> And in gaining a Man that they had so sensibly disobliged, and who of all others was in least hazard of being suspected by the States, the <hi>French</hi> have given us a remarkable instance, both of their cunning, and of <hi>the Means and Power they have to corrupt Men into their In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terest.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="31" facs="tcp:99113:18"/>
            <p>It may perhaps be expected that a Character should be here given of the rest of the Conspirators; but the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spiracy it self lays it sufficiently open, what sort of Men they must needs be that could enter into it. Only this may be further said of them in short; Monsieur <hi>Bedall</hi> is the Son of a Merchant in <hi>Paris,</hi> who has since been ena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled in <hi>Sweden,</hi> under the Title of Baron of <hi>Alsfield.</hi> He has all his life-time been but little obliged to Fame, and ever passed for a Man capable of any sort of Villa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, that might serve to make his Court, or raise his For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune.</p>
            <p>Monsieur <hi>Paparell</hi> was born and educated a Protestant, and changed his Religion to ingratiate himself with the Court, being look'd upon as guilty of a great many gross Immoralities in his Life, and one that adores no other Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinity than that of <hi>Lewis</hi> the Great.</p>
            <p>Monsieur <hi>Chanlais</hi> has ever till now appeared a Man of more Honour than most of the Court of <hi>France</hi> are; he passes for a Man of Intriegue and Parts, and was thought a fit Person to be employed the last year to manage an Accommodation betwixt the <hi>French</hi> King and the Duke of <hi>Savoy:</hi> But it seems he has at length sacrific'd his Reputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and Virtue to an irregular Ambition, and a desire to please his Master.</p>
            <p>As to our <hi>English</hi> Champion, <hi>Parker,</hi> his Character is well-known here, and is very apparent by the villa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous Part he has acted in this Conspiracy. But there is one thing relating to this Man's share of the Plot, that must not be passed over in silence, and which brings us to look back to the time in which this Villany was to be executed.</p>
            <p>It was thought strange, that the <hi>French</hi> were no earlier in the Field this Spring, considering that their greatest advantange lies in being able to draw their Forces out of their Winter Quarters sooner than the Confederates, for
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:99113:19"/> the most part, can do. But they were resolved this year to play all their Engines at once, <hi>The French King was to be in</hi> Flanders, Namur <hi>was to be besieged, King</hi> James <hi>was to Land in</hi> England, <hi>and His Majesty was to be Murdered, all about the same time.</hi> To nothing else, but <hi>the concert<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>se Designs together,</hi> can the delay of the <hi>French</hi> King's Journey to <hi>Flanders,</hi> from day to day, for more than six Weeks together be attributed.</p>
            <p>But there is this yet to be further remark'd, That at the same time that <hi>Grandvall</hi> and <hi>Leefdale</hi> take journey from <hi>Paris</hi> to <hi>Flanders,</hi> Parker <hi>comes over to</hi> England. We have all reason to remember the great hopes our Male<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>contents exprest here at that time, and how sure they seemed to be of some <hi>new Revolution.</hi> It's true, these people are easily buoyed up upon the least appearances; and every small Accident that seems to favour their Cause, raises their hopes beyond all bounds. But about that time, so much joy and assurance was visible in their very Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenances, as seem'd to proceed from a fixt certainty they had, of some mighty Success which they hoped for in their Affairs, that we could not possibly dive into. It's true, the <hi>French</hi> King was in <hi>Flanders,</hi> and King <hi>James</hi> was waiting the first opportunity of Wind and Tide to waft over his Army into <hi>England;</hi> But even all this could scarce make up more than a <hi>Probability,</hi> much less a <hi>Certainty</hi> of Success. His Majesty was already on the other side, and his Army was drawing together from all Quarters to oppose the <hi>French.</hi> Our Fleet was at Sea, and a far braver one it was, than the <hi>French</hi> could possibly send out against us. Whence then could all this Confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence proceed? There must certainly be some other thing in it than we were then aware of.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Parker</hi>'s coming over at that time, and his correspond<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with his Friends here, carries with it a shrowd suspi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of what we may reasonably judge was the ground
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:99113:19"/> of all this Insolence of the Party. — It were folly to ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine he should make publick among them, the Design then in agitation <hi>to murther the King:</hi> It was too great a Secret to be communicated to many. But on the other hand, it's scarce to be thought, but that <hi>Parker</hi> assured his Friends in general, <hi>That there was some great and cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain Event ready then to break forth, that would decide the Controversie;</hi> and he might even venture to open the Secret to some of the first <hi>form</hi> amongst them.</p>
            <p>It were harsh, and might seem severe to suppose, that our Malecontents could be brought in, either to contrive or consent to murther His Majesty in cold blood, though 'tis to be feared there may be found among them some more than <hi>Parker,</hi> capable of so much wickedness: yet it's not to be doubted, but the most part, if not at all of them, would have heartily embraced the advantage of such a Conjuncture as that which must needs have attended the Blow, and then have satisfied their own Consciences and Honour, by putting a distinction betwixt the Treason and the Traytor. They might abhor that Villany, and yet strive to reap all the profit they could from it: for it were too severe a trial of their Vertue to hope they would have changed Parties upon such an Accident.</p>
            <p>It remains only, that we should take notice of His Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jesty's Carriage, as to <hi>Grandvall</hi>'s Tryal. In <hi>Flanders,</hi> and all other Countries where Torture is admitted, never any Assassinate escaped it, but he. It is not looked upon as a sufficient ground to excuse a Criminal from it, that he voluntarily confesses his Indictment. On the contrary, if there lie probable grounds of Suspicion of any one as <hi>Accessary,</hi> that he does not name in his voluntary. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fession, the Criminal is put to the Torture, to answer, <hi>Whether that Person suspected, be accessary to the Crime or not.</hi> Now in this Case, there were the greatest pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sumptions that possibly could be, of the <hi>French</hi> King's be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:99113:20"/> concerned; and doubtless the Councel of War (as every body else that's not prejudiced) were of that Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion. Yet all this could not prevail with His Majesty to put this Wretch to the <hi>Torture,</hi> nor was he put so much as in <hi>Irons</hi> (the Fate of every ordinary Felon); <hi>a Generosity without Example!</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But that <hi>Grandvall</hi> kept a reserve with respect to the <hi>French</hi> King, in the whole thread of his Deportment and Confession, is very probable: He saw there was no neces<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sity put upon him to confess more than what <hi>Leefdale, Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mont,</hi> and <hi>D' Amours,</hi> either had or could depose against him: He knew they could say nothing of the <hi>French</hi> King in the Affair, and indeed were acquainted with little more than what he himself thought fit to tell them, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving lain under no temptation to name the <hi>French</hi> King to them, though he had known him to be concerned; it being enough that what was promised them, was in <hi>Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>besieux</hi>'s name. Upon all which Considerations, and that he was to die however, and that without any previous Torture to oblige him to a further Confession, he had been a Mad-man indeed to have needlesly acknowledged any thing that might immediately reflect upon his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster, of whose glory the Action it self, for which he was executed, shews him to have been an Idolater.</p>
            <p>There might likewise be another Motive to induce a Man that knew himself without the compass of a Pardon, to use <hi>some Reserve.</hi> He left Friends behind him, and par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly the Lady to whom he writ his last Letter, men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned in his Tryal, who is thought to have been his Mistress; and it was but reasonable to him to hope he might, by observing so great a respect to the <hi>French</hi> King at his Death, <hi>oblige him to take some care, both of her, and of his other Relations after he was gone.</hi> The Letter he wrote to this Lady, carries with it something of <hi>Mystery,</hi> and would seem to point towards some what of this kind.
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:99113:20"/> Sure there was no need for him to desire <hi>her to go to the Archbishop of</hi> Rheims, <hi>to tell him, That it cost him his Life for having obeyed the Orders of Monsieur</hi> d' Barbesieux: Since his own publick Confession told that, which he might well imagine would be carried to all the Nations of <hi>Christendom,</hi> and to the Court of <hi>France,</hi> as soon as to any; therefore it is but reasonable to suppose, that some hidden Intimation was given to the Archbishop of <hi>Rheims</hi> by this strange kind of Letter, which tho we do not un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstand, the Archbishop himself, no doubt, does.</p>
            <p>I have done with this Paper, and tremble to think, for I am sure I cannot reckon up, what the Consequences of this Assassination would have been, if the Anger of Heaven had, for the Punishment of our Sins, suffered it to take its effect. They are much more easy to be imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned than express'd. <hi>Minds less black than theirs, who contrived it, can hardly conceive what a Scene of Barbari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and Cruelty, of Blood and Horror, must have followed upon it.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:99113:21"/>
            <head>BOOKS Printed for <hi>R. Baldwin.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>THE Speech of the Right Honourable <hi>Henry</hi> Earl of <hi>Warrington,</hi> Lord <hi>Delamere,</hi> to the Grand Jury at <hi>Chester, April</hi> 13. 1692.</p>
            <p>The Speech of the Right Honourable <hi>Thomas</hi> Earl of <hi>Stamford,</hi> Lord <hi>Gray</hi> of <hi>Greoby,</hi> &amp;c. at the General Quarter-Sessions held for the County of <hi>Leicester,</hi> at Michaelmas, 1691. His Lordship being made <hi>Custos Rotulorum</hi> for the said County, by the late Lord Commissioners of the Great Seal.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>State Tracts;</hi> being a farther Collection of several Choice Treatises relating to the Government, from the year 1660. to 1689. Now published in a Body, to shew the Necessity and clear the Legality of the late Revolution, and our present happy Settlement, under the Auspicious Reign of Their Majesties King <hi>William</hi> and Queen <hi>Mary.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Saul</hi> at <hi>Endor:</hi> Or the Ghost of the Marquiss <hi>de Louvois</hi> consulted by the <hi>French</hi> King, concerning the present Affairs. <hi>Done out of</hi> French.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Europe</hi>'s Chains broke; or a sure and speedy Project to Rescue Her from the present Usurpations of the Tyrant of <hi>France.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A Faithful Account of the Renewed Persecution of the Churches of <hi>Lower Aquitaine</hi> in <hi>France,</hi> in the year 1692. To which is prefixed a Parallel between the Ancient and New Persecutors; or the Portaicture of <hi>Lewis</hi> XIV. in some of his Cruelties and Barbarities. With some Reflections upon the unreasonable Fondness of a certain Party amongst us, for the <hi>French</hi> King.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Bibliotheca Politica;</hi> Or a Discourse by way of Dialogue, <hi>Whether Absolute Non-Resistance of the Supreme Powers be enjoined by the Doctrine of the Gospel, and was the Ancient Practise of the Primitive Church, and the constant Doctrine of our Reformed Church of England.</hi> Collected out of the most approved Authors, both Ancient and Modern. <hi>Dialogue the Fourth.</hi> Printed for <hi>R. Baldwin;</hi> where also may be had the <hi>First, Second,</hi> and <hi>Third Dialogues.</hi> The <hi>Fifth</hi> is in the Press and will be Published in a few days.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Truth brought to Light;</hi> or the History of the first 14 years of K. <hi>James</hi> I. In Four Parts. I. The happy state of <hi>England</hi> at his Majesty's Entrance; the corruption of it afterwards. With the Rise of Particular Favourites, and the Divisions between this and other States abroad. II. The Divorce betwixt the Lady <hi>Frances Howard,</hi> and <hi>Robert</hi> Earl of <hi>Essex,</hi> before the King's Delegates, authorized under the King's Broad-Seal: As also the Arraignment of Sir <hi>Jer. Ellis,</hi> Lieutenant of the <hi>Tower, &amp;c.</hi> about the murther of Sir. <hi>Tho. Over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bury,</hi> with all Proceedings thereupon, and the King's gracious Pardon and Favour to the Countess. III. A Declaration of his Majesty's Revenue since he came to the Crown of <hi>England;</hi> with the Annual Issues, Gifts, Pensions, and extraordinary Disbursements. IV. The Commissions and Warrants for the burning of two Hereticks, newly revived, with two Pardons, one for <hi>Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>philus Higgons,</hi> the other for Sir <hi>Eustace Hart.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Cabinet opened; or the Secret History of the Amours of Madam <hi>de Maintenon,</hi> with the <hi>French</hi> King. <hi>Translated from the</hi> French Copy.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>